Curiculum vitae.

(Postdoctoral fellow, PluriCourts)

Name: Silje Synnøve Lyder Adress: Sandakerveien 22C

Hermansen 0374 Oslo

Born: 22.09.1981 Email: s.s.l.hermansen@jus.uio.no

Telephone: 40 49 91 07 Web: siljehermansen.github.io

Publications:

2020 "Delegation of Committee Reports in the European Parliament", with Bjørn Høyland (University of Oslo) and Fang-Yi Chiou (Academie Sinica, Taiwan). European Union

Politics. Forthcoming.

2019 Lær deg R: En innføring i statistikkprogrammets muligheter. Fagbokforlaget, Oslo, 224

p.

2018 "Striving for influence: The effect of performance on candidate selection". Party

Politics, 24 (4), pp 382-396

2018 "(Self-)selection and expertise among decision-makers in the European Parliament".

The Journal of Legislative Studies, 24 (1), pp 148-172

Submitted: "Tending the Bar: Strategic Case Allocations in the Court of Justice of the European

Union", single-authored. Invited contribution to *Journal of European Public Policy*'s series

on EUSA 2019 Best Papers.

Working papers: "Will Do? Selecting Judges on Preferences and Performance", with Daniel Naurin

(PluriCourts)

"Blurred Lines: The Use of Constituency-Based Assistants among Election Seekers",

with Andreja Pegan (Northumbria University).

"The sanction that isn't imposed? Roll-call voting loyalty and demotion in European

Parliament elections" with Mihail Chiru (UCLouvain) and Thomas Däubler (University of

Mannheim)

"How Do Legislated Gender Quotas Impact Representation?", single-authored.

"A different voice in International Courts? Gender and Judicial Behavior in Sexual and

Reproductive Rights", with Malcolm Langford, Daniel Naurin and Vegard Vibe

Teaching:

Author: Lær deg R: En innføring I statistikkprogrammets muligheter (Introductory book to

statistical programming, 2019)

Profession courses:

Data management in R for practitioners (Course at Unit – Norwegian Directorate for

Information Technologies in Research and Higher Education, 2019)

Lectures: Statistical analysis (masters and phd level, University of Oslo, 2019)

Research methods and statistics for political scientists (masters level, University of Oslo,

2012, 2013, 2014)

Research methods and statistics in peace and conflict studies (masters level, University

of Oslo, 2015)

Research methods and statistics for political scientists (bachelors level, University College

Østfold, 2013)

Seminar leader:

EU decision-making processes and policy areas (bachelors level, University of Oslo, 2015)

European Union institutions (bachelors level, University of Oslo, 2012)

Political analysis (supervision of bachelors thesis, University of Oslo, 2012)

Quantitative methods (masters level, 2011, 2013, 2014)

Evaluation: I have also graded in various theses and courses in comparative politics, political analysis

and research methods at the bachelors' and masters' level.

Academic background:

Positions:

05.17 – current **Assistant professor/Post. Doc.**

Research area: Independence and accountability as well as judicial behavior in international courts with a special focus on

the Court of Justice of the European Union.

08.11 – 01.17 PhD in Political Science

Title: «Choosing Agents: Members of the European Parliament and their Political Organizations Seen through Report

Allocation»

Questions: What are the considerations that European political groups make when delegating legislative tasks? How do these allocations impact national parties' choice of

candidates?

I relied on predictions from theories of legislative organization and democratic accountability which I tested using quantitative methods and original data.

The position included 25% teaching obligations. I held lectures and led seminars in quantitative research methods, decision-making processes in the EU as well as advising on the bachelor's thesis.

Department of Political Science University of Oslo

PluriCourts

University of Oslo

I had two maternity leaves during my contract: One in the winter of 2012/13 and a second in the autumn of 2015.

	winter of 2012/13 and a second in the autumn of 2015.	
2018	Summer schools School: "Methods for Computational Social Science" Course: Analyzing and modeling textual data	University of Southern California (Los Angeles)
2014	School: "EITM Europe — Empirical implications of theoretical models". Course: Theoretical and Methodological Foundations and Accountability and Violence	University of Mannheim (Mannheim)
2013	School: "Parliamentary democracy in Europe" Course: The European Parliament: Intra- and Inter- Institutional Politics and The Rules and Functions of the European Parliament	LUISS Guido Carlo School of Government (Rome)
2012	School: ICPSR Summer Program in Quantitative Methods of Social Research Course: Introduction to Applied Bayesian Modeling for the Social Sciences, Introduction to Game Theory and Advanced Game Theory	University of Michigan (Ann Arbor)
2011	School: Essex Summer School in Social Sciences, University of Essex Course: Single Course in Hierarchical Models	Universitetet i Essex (Essex)
02.17-05.17	Writer's grant I have written an introductory book in R (statistics program) for students in social sciences. (publication 2019)	Fagbokforlaget
08.13-12.13	Visiting Lecturer Teaching introductory course in Research Methods and Statistics.	Østfold University College
Education:		
08.07 - 05.10	Master in political science My master's thesis did a quantitative study of decision- making/internal organaization in the European Parliament. The degree also included a semester of Research Methods, as well as single courses in International Security Politics, International Negotiations and Game Theory, Oil- and Energy Policy and EU Institutions.	University of Oslo
	In 2008-09, I took a year off to lead the students' magazine Argument.	

09.01 - 07.05 Bachelor in political science

Research assistant

Single courses in political science

03.07 - 09.08

08.06 - 12.06

Consists in two years of law ("DEUG de droit") and an additional year of political science ("Licence de science politique")

University of Oslo
Université Panthéon-Sorbonne

University of Oslo

Paris

Baccalauréat français

I did my high school in France as an exchange student. After three months of intensive language courses, I integrated a regular French class. Lycée Alain Chartier Bayeux

Conferences:

American Political Science Association (Washington DC, 2014; Boston, 2018)

European Consortium of Political science (ECPR) General Conference (Oslo, 2017; Wrocław 2019) European Political Science Association (Barcelona, 2013; Edinburgh, 2014; Brussels, 2016; Vienna, 2018; Belfast, 2019)

European Union Studies Association (Denver, 2019)

Global and Regional Governance, workshop (Stockholm, 2017)

Joint Sessions (ECPR) (Mons, 2019)

Midwest Political Science Association (Chicago, 2014; 2015)

Norwegian National Conference in Political Science (Trondheim, 2012; Tromsø, 2014; Oslo, 2015, Stavanger 2017, Bergen 2018; Trondheim, 2019)

Standing Group on European Union (ECPR) (Hague, 2014; Trento 2016; Paris, 2018)

Standing Group on Parliaments (ECPR) (Munich, 2016)

Invited talks:

Departemental seminar (Center for European Law, University of Oslo, 2019)

Departmental seminar (University College London, 2019)

Expert Meeting on the Design of a Multilateral Investment Court (European Commission, 2018)

Comparative Institutions and Regimes Seminar (University of Oslo, 2018)

Bergen Exchanges on Law & Social Transformation (University of Bergen, 2017)

PADEMIA workshop on Parliamentary accountability: Assessing the link between citizens and elites in national and supranational politics (University College Dublin, 2016)

PADEMIA workshop on Recent Developments in the studies of the European Parliament (College of Europe, 2015)

Service:

Reviewer: European Union Politics, Journal of Common Market Studies, Journal of Legislative Studies,

Scandinavian Political Studies, Journal of European Integration

Organizer: Panel: "Quantitative methods", Norwegian National Conference in Political Science

(Trondheim, 2019)

Other experiences:

01.11-08.11 Higher Executive Officer

Ministry of Transport and Communications

Department of Public Roads and Traffic Safety (Section for Traffic Safety and Civil Emergency Planning)

06.08-06.09 Editor in Chief argument:

Argument is an interdisciplinary students' newspaper. I have previously had the position as section editor, member of the editorial team and writer for the same paper.

1998-2007 Editorial Assistant

Egmont Serieforlaget

Egmont Serieforlaget - comic books.

Summer job: My main responsabilities evolved over time from assisting in ongoing projects of archivation to keeping the wheels

turning while the editors went on holidays.

2004-2016 Freelance

Parttime translator (French/Norwegian, Norwegian/French, English/Norwegian), proofreader, editor, consultant (reader's

reports).

Egmont Serieforlaget, Universitetsforlaget Forum for universitetshistorie

KUNSTforum

02.06-06.06 **Student Intern**

The internship is intended to give hands-on experience with state administration to students with knowledge of French

language and society.

Royal Norwegian Embassy

in Paris

Voluntary positions:

2014-2015 **Board Member** University of Oslo

Department of Political Science (Oslo)

09.05-09.10 **Elected – Søndre Nordstrand District Council** Bydelsutvalget

(Oslo)

2004-2005 **Board Member** Université Panthéon-Sorbonne

Department of Political Science. (Paris)

Languages:

NorwegianNative speaker.RProficientFrenchProficient.PythonBasicEngelskProficient.LaTeX/MarkdownProficient